34. Are you addicted to the Internet? Internet addiction is a relatively new and
controversial disorder. Though it is still not recognized as a specific disorder by all
doctors, many people see the signs of Internet overuse in their lives and are trying to fight
it. Most compulsive Internet users are hooked on a few specific activities—online buying
or gambling, online relationships, including social networking, computer games, and compulsive
data searching. These are activities that many of us often perform. Some people, however,
find them hard to stop. Their online activities may become more important than their real-life
activities. They may allow relationships to die because they only spend time with Internet
friends. They may be unable to stop playing computer games and ignore chores or family
time. People often turn to the Internet for stress relief or to get away from their problems
for a few minutes. However, some people may become too dependent on escaping into the Internet.
The Internet becomes a destructive force in their lives. To check for possible Internet
addiction or compulsion, doctors will ask you a few key questions. They ask about whether
spending time online is affecting your school or work performance. They ask if family or
friends complain about your Internet use and if you form more new relationships online
than offline. They ask if you worry that life without the Internet would be useless and
boring, if you often stay online longer than you intended, or if you lie about how long you've been
in front of the computer. We use the Internet so much that when it becomes an unhealthy addiction,
it can be hard to spot. Think carefully about how you use the Internet. Even useful tools can be
dangerous.